[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa everyone i am peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
there still is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of this very moment
and for those of you who are new uh
visiting the stoa we've
found we've been around for about six
months um
i don't know what we are a digital
campfire we have a wisdom gym where we
have a
regular reoccurring events and a
communal podcast
so instead of just a 101 interview with
someone the group the collective
intelligence
of the zoom room of the stoa is
leveraged
to ask questions to our guest
and we also have sensemaker in residence
series where a sensemaker who's trying
to make sense of the world comes in for
about a month four sessions
um to have one of these communal podcast
things and we just had dave snowden uh
uh since making mensch uh earlier uh
today
uh who created the kinetic framework so
today we're very lucky because we got
joe norman uh
at the stoa um so our mc of today
is going to introduce joe in a moment
and that is ryan
wong uh narayan is um co-founder of a
non-profit in toronto called think
better and he's
he geeks out on system thinking
complexity and applied rationality
so i'm going to take narayan in and he's
going to explain how today's going to go
and he's going to introduce joe and then
we'll go from there
so ryan i will take you in
hi everyone so a couple of housekeeping
items
for how the format of today is going to
work so
joe norman is here to share
his knowledge and his wisdom and today
we're going to be going in an interview
format
so i'm going to start off with a couple
of warm-up questions questions
just to sort of explore the topic on a
more general basis
and if something comes up for you feel
free to type your question into the chat
and feel free to also specify if you'd
like to read it out loud or if you want
me to read it for you
i'm happy to read your questions as well
i'm not necessarily going to
read them in the order that they come
but i'm going to try and facilitate
a coherent conversation and so feel free
to also
plus one each other's questions so that
i can figure out
what is alive with the audience um
to go along with this this will go on
youtube
so if you're not comfortable um with
that
feel free to turn off your camera but
this whole audio session will be
recorded
so just an fyi from that
and yeah so i'm super excited for
today's
session um i've been doing a little bit
of complexity work recently i'm
currently hiring for a complexity
analyst so
i'm really excited to hear uh what joe
has to say
um joe norman is an applied complexity
scientist
with a focus on transforming insights
gleaned from complex systems
science into practical and implementable
strategies
and tactics for grappling with an
increasingly uncertain
and dynamic world joe is an affiliate of
the new england complex systems
institute
in cambridge ma an instructor
at the real world risk institute and
founder of applied complexity science
llc he lives in new hampshire with his
wife where they are focusing their
energy on homesteading
and local agriculture on an old mill
property that has been an actively
running homestead for over 130 years
so welcome joe
thank you
so i guess to start off with um joe
what for those of us who are still
struggling to understand what is
complexity and what is applied
complexity i guess can you share
your your understanding of how you use
the term complexity
and what applied complexity sort of
means to you
yeah absolutely um so complexity and
complex system science
the idea of complex system science in
its essence is really looking
at how things interact
and how those interactions give rise to
properties and behaviors
of systems um that you won't
be able to discover or observe
if you break the system down into
isolated components and study it that
way
so it's sort of the complement or or it
contains the complement to
reductionism a reductionist approach to
science
where the driving philosophy is just
that you have a system you're interested
in you're interested in some
uh behaviors or aspects of that system
and you want to break it down into its
smallest pieces generally and study
those pieces
and the the thinking goes the philosophy
goes of reductionism
that you'll be able to put those pieces
back together again in a fairly
straightforward way
and understand how the whole system
works based on
studying just those parts cut apart
literally analyzed
split into parts and dissected into
pieces so it turns out that
um when you dissect a system and you
you don't allow the components to
interact anymore
you destroy a lot of the information
about the system and there's no
way to recover it without looking at the
system as a whole looking at those
interactions
so that's the essential um piece of
complexity
that some of the other sciences or or
some of the other philosophies
uh can miss and um
the the one of the consequences of this
is complexity is
in some sense the um study of
organization as such so you're not
necessarily studying
biological systems or chemical systems
or social systems
you're looking at how each of these
systems that are in a particular
medium or composed of a particular
substance you're looking
at how it's arranged or composed
or organized and and um
trying to understand how the interesting
properties
or the relevant properties are coming
out of that organization and those
interactions
um and now that that's really complex
systems theory
and um there's a lot of
history of this there's histories of
different sciences that feed into it
you know systems theory general systems
theory cybernetics to name some
um and it's really now on all under this
umbrella of complex system science
and the thing about that is when we when
we go to actually apply
uh what we learn from complex system
science it turns out there's some
implications
for what it means to apply science um
it looks a little different than applied
science might generally look which is
often thought of as kind of
uh taking some known facts about some
system and applying it to produce a
technology for instance
this is more about what are the
principles
and and kind of uh meta lessons we're
learning from studying complexity
and what are the implications from those
for when we interact with complex
systems in the world when we intervene
with them when we attempt to synthesize
them etc
um so so that's sort of complexity and
then a little bit of a
gesture in the direction of applied
complexity
does that kind of make sense
yeah i'm thinking of like
this might be a weird parallel to draw
but the movement between um
sort of like the rationality community
and then the fact that there's an
applied rationality
um sort of branch of that that looks at
we've taken all these lessons from
this way of seeing the world and here's
how we actually apply it in real life
and what i've found is that the practice
often looks a little bit different than
what the theory suggests
so i'm wondering joe um
what are some of the ways that we might
be able to spot a complex situation
or a place in which applied complexity
might be relevant
and what are some of the tools that
an applied complexity wizard might be uh
drawn to using so
spotting it you know
complex systems you know complexity is
one of those things that you often hear
like you know when you see it right
but the truth is that one of one of the
insights that comes out of studying
complexity
is that we've done a bit of an inversion
with science
where we've treated very special kinds
of systems linear systems simple systems
isolated systems equilibrium systems
as the general case and we've treated
complex systems as a kind of special
case
of a very particular kind of arrangement
of these these more general simple
systems
when in fact uh the world that we
encounter the world that we're
interested in
interacting in and acting in
it's it's the other way around
complexity is the general case almost
everything that we interact with in some
sense by definition if we're interacting
with it it's now a non-isolated system
so complexity is everywhere pretty much
every problem we're looking at in the
world right now
is a complex problem the parts are not
independent
they are interdependent and uh when you
push over here
things happen over here and over here
and you can't uh
a priori track all those relationships i
mean for many reasons there's opacity of
the system in the sense that
um is there just too much to see
how the causal paths might be arranged
and
what might actually be touching what in
some sense so
the the spotting of complexity it's
almost trivial
it's almost trivial um it's probably
less trivial to spot the cases where we
could actually
apply um linear models or
or equilibrium models and and they
actually hold
in any set of relevant conditions um
and so tools to bring to bear so so
there's a lot of modeling tools that are
associated with um complexity science
for the reason that they draw out a lot
of these features that i'm talking about
like there's
multiple parts that are interacting a
lot and those interactions become
relevant to the to the dynamics of the
system
um so it's not so much
which tools you bring as how you use
them
and so for instance if you let's say
you're building a computational model of
some system
a say the global air travel system
and you're interested in looking at
pandemics or something
the idea in applied complexity isn't
necessarily to try to
build a faithful model of the system and
then use it to predict the future states
so much as to to surface the assumptions
that become very explicit as you build
the model
and then to start probing and
questioning those assumptions are these
the right assumptions are they the wrong
assumptions
if they're the right assumptions then uh
you you might get something where you
can do something like prediction or
forecasting but that's very rare
and most of the time you have in a
complex system some
incorrect assumptions and spotting and
finding those and finding the ones that
are are critical is uh exactly what we
should be doing with models in in
practice now of course if you're doing
theoretical work and uh you're working
in the lab and you're not
concerned with the real world so to
speak then
there's a lot of ways to go but when
you're when you're applying these things
you it's it's truly critical to
um question your own assumptions and and
models help to surface those so things
like agent-based models
um are are really helpful in doing that
cool so sort of what i'm hearing from
you is that
complexity there's not really a lot of
use cases where it's
useful to say let's point at the
complexity here it's kind of like saying
the
um it's almost more rare to say this
this situation is actually not complex
and that's the that's the more rare
thing to spot
and in terms of i mean things things in
general are not not isolated
things in general are are touching
they're part of the world
interconnected yeah and i think you
you're just
mentioning that one of the things that
one might do is
rather than trying to build a model to
predict um what you'd want to do is
actually look at the underlying
assumptions that you're using to build
the model
and that's where the interest lies um
so at this point i'd like to welcome
other people to start dropping in more
questions
into the chat um whatever's been coming
up for you
and i think i've got one other question
for you joe
um which is i'm wondering if you can
give us an example
of some of the work that you've done
like what is a complex problem that
you've actually
worked on and what would be sort of like
the wrong approach and then contrast
that to the approach that you actually
took
and sort of why is why is applied
complex complexity the the right
approach for this
so i mean recent example is uh
the coronavirus issue and back in
january
i wrote a paper along with naseem talib
and yunir baryam and we said
look this thing is something we need to
take very seriously we need to
apply precautionary measures immediately
not because we know
it will be bad but because based on what
we do know it could be really bad
so what are the assumptions we were
working with there
uh that were counter to some other
assumptions well one
is that the dynamics are multiplicative
meaning one person gets sick they get
more than one person sick more than one
person we all
are probably familiar by now with this
are not idea
that are not as such has some issues as
a as a parameter to rely on in any sense
but just as a multiplicative
process and two our assumption is the
world
is very very closely
interconnected so we are living in a
small world
in the most extreme way there's very few
hops between
any two people choose any two random
people on earth how many hops does it
take in terms of interpersonal contact
for one person to reach another very few
no one knows the
true answer but i mean we're talking
like a handful maybe
max you know five four very few hops
so everyone's very close in in
topological space
and um it is this topology combined with
multiplicative dynamics that puts no
upper bound on a spread of a
contagious disease like that and so we
pointed to that we said this is
this is exactly a scenario where you
take precaution and so
there's you know there's other things
you can do
for for disease those things can be you
know
vaccine development and therapeutics and
all those are good things
um but they're fundamentally the wrong
uh
scale to begin on uh the right scale to
begin on
is to first kind of um
in a sense and it's i'm not implying
lockdowns but
freeze in place in the sense of cut all
non-essential travel
this is not a permanent thing it's an
adaptive decoupling
um gain some it's really like an ooda
loop almost if you're familiar with with
that idea
uh orient to the issue um start to
become more sensitive put resources into
sensitizing yourself where is this thing
where is it not
and um you know you might have heard
this idea of like a green zone red zone
strategy
start implementing these spatial
strategies where you start clearing
zones and then you expand the zones in
which you're clearing
obviously at least here in the u.s we
didn't take this strategy
at all and that's why we're still
dealing with this thing
so i'm not going to say that we dealt
with this successfully because clearly
we're still dealing with this problem
but i think our approach to the to the
way we're thinking about this
um shows that there's actually a few
very call them simple underlying
uh details of the system and let's just
first pay attention to those
and and attack those and and then let's
get the other things in let's do
vaccines let's uh let's do testing let's
do contact tracing
all of those things should come after um
prior to that so another example a
little different
setting is a few years ago i went down
and
did a fellowship with the u.s special
operations command
and they were having issues with um
well frankly understanding themselves
they knew that they
were very successful in certain contexts
and they were perceived that way as well
and
in government it's all about fighting
for money so
all of these different fiefdoms are just
fighting for the same dollars
and so they were trying to figure out
kind of
how they make their case for their
dollars frankly and
um in making that case articulating
their unique value in what they do
so interestingly because they had been
they were being they were successful in
some sense and they were being perceived
as successful the dollars were flowing
to them already
and they found that they were starting
to have more problems after the dollar
started to flow
and so what was happening well it turns
out that what was happening was
as they were getting uh more capital
more
more monetary resources they were
bureaucratizing
and that bureaucratizing was making them
more uniform
across their their approaches their
teams their operations how they operated
and the the piece that they were missing
was that
the standardization uh that they were
they were
kind of going through was actually
removing their value and their value was
actually
maintaining independence among
individuals among teams
among approaches and operations and so
they were actually
uh their success was undercutting their
values so we did a study
with them and and drew that out and
hopefully convinced them or at least
some of them that um
you know fight for your money sure but
um you need to maintain independence
among these units
the the the tendency is for things to to
become bureaucratic and centralized
and for that independence to break down
um and if you're dealing with
the fine-grained complexity that uh
special operations are dealing with
then that's actually um a hindrance not
a help
so that's another example of where we
applied some systems thinking to
to a problem thanks
that really helps grow me up um
jacob spence has a question would you
like to read that out loud jacob
sure um i was curious if in your
history of uh coming about to complexity
as a thing that you study
and apply um if this had sort of always
piqued your interest and it just grew
and developed
um or if you had any sort of turning
point where you were
all about applying like the latest
linear equilibrium models and then
you're like oh that
had a seeing the light moment
frame shift you know actually i've
um i've benefited from the fact that
my father worked in complex systems he's
actually a pioneer in
complex systems engineering and the
truth is
that the earliest memory i have of
having an aha moment
was sitting on the toilet and i picked
up
a book that was sitting there sync by
stephen strogatz and started reading on
it
and um that's when it first started
clicking to me you know he's talking
about
fireflies and and distributed
self-organizing
emerging patterns of their
synchronization and that that's when
complexity started clicking for me
uh truly and i'd say the other um
experience i had when i was younger uh
was through music
and i think that most musicians will
find um
complexity pretty natural in that music
is
almost purely relational um so
for instance um when you play a chord
say on a piano you're playing more than
one note
right and the quality that arises from
from a chord is not like individual
notes
added together it's something new that
none of the notes themselves
have possessed there's no quality of
harmony in a single note and um
moreover things like major and minor
chords can be constructed from
sort of a infinite set of of different
unique notes but they retain some
quality among them because of that
relation between them so i think
as well music uh kind of primed me to
see that way
um and i
let's see then in um
undergrad i was started getting
interested in cognitive science and
philosophy of mind
and once again it it became imminently
clear
that uh the folks who were bringing
clarity to the situation were always
invoking uh
relational issues so you have things
like um affordances as percepts so
affordances are come from jj gibson
where he talks about perception as
perceiving opportunities for action
so opportunities for action for who for
the agent well
what's an opportunity for action well
depends on for instance the shape of
your body the anatomy of your body
uh like what do you see when you see a
branch well it's kind of graspable
and i can hang on it um these are
not something that's in the branch these
are not something that's in the body
these are something that's relational
between these things so that was another
um that was another kind of set of
experiences that that started to
reinforce that idea that really
it's in the interaction and the relation
between all these parts that the things
that i'm interested in exist
and i've just kind of continued on a
continuous path towards complexity there
was never
besides that the toilet moment with
steven strogatz
there was never really a single turning
point that i could i could point to
let's go to uh matthew stevenson with
his question
oh i will read it for you um so
this is going in a bit of a different
direction but wondering does your
experience in complexity
motivate the more localized homesteading
way of life you practice
and if so what areas of modernity
are you trying to mitigate through this
lifestyle
in part it certainly motivates it um
one of the things and this is related to
the discussion on on the
covid pandemic because of how
interdependent we are at such large
scales now global scales
for pretty much everything every good
every service everything is touching
everywhere
we've set ourselves up for for quite a
set of tail risks and
i i'm sorry to say that kovid
is just a preview um this is not like oh
this once in a million-year thing
happened and nothing like swept no this
we are connected we are more connected
than ever
um if we don't learn our lessons from
this we'll continue in that direction
which is probably the case um
and so certainly um developing some
personal redundancy that is for
my family myself to um not depend
on what's produced halfway around the
globe
sets us up for when some of these tail
risk events happen hey we have some shot
here
you know we anyone can be overcome by
events there's no
panacea yet um if you have no redundancy
if you have nothing to fall back on
locally
then you're really in a tough spot
whereas if you
you know you can't be purely
self-sufficient as an individual of
course i mean i guess you could but you
wouldn't
uh wouldn't have much of a life beyond
that self-sufficiency but at
very small scales you can actually be
quite comfortably self-sufficient say
scale of the size of a
i don't know of the size of new
hampshire where i live i
i am certainly convinced that almost
everything that we need to be
live comfortable life could be produced
in new hampshire um
now new hampshire could have a natural
disaster and then we could rely on our
neighbors vermont
maine massachusetts but that sort of
scaling up of reliance should be
something that's happening dynamically
in response to needs rather than
something that's
that's the norm and now you depend on in
a existential way
so yeah there's definitely a uh
motivating
factor from from from thinking about
complexity and the need for
um independence among some of the
components um
for for survival reasons that motivates
it and
and you know um things like permaculture
and regenerative agriculture caught my
eye before
we made a move like this and things i
started reading up on
and it's just another way of
interacting with the world and and being
in the world
that
that seems to not um be at odds
with with the natural um cycle of things
and and the natural tendencies of the
world whereas
the way we've industrialized things and
and tried our best
and failed in most cases to to um
build a mechanical vision of the world
at scale
um i just i see that i see how it's
constantly at tension with
the way ecosystems work the way all our
life support systems work
and the way it can undercut them and
just i just have no desire
to to participate that if i can avoid it
to the degree that i can avoid it to the
degree that i can
go a different way and and make some
small
incremental tiny move towards something
that i that i
feel more right about
you're not the only person who's
interested in complexity that i know
that is also doing a homesteading style
thing i know i think i can point my
finger at
at least two or three others and
it's interesting to think okay joe
norman
is thinking and he's seeing the world in
a way that's different from how i'm
seeing it
i would like to be able to think in the
ways that you're thinking
and i imagine that it's still quite a
rare
way of thinking or a rare way of
interpreting the world and it seems very
valuable to me
um so i'm actually going to point at
josh
field to ask his question next
hey uh my question is just uh
how should oh sorry should complex
systems thinking be taught
um and included in school curriculums
and what are some
core principles and concepts that are
necessary for children to grasp with
regards to complexity
so i if if i were running a course if i
were running a school i would certainly
teach it
but i wouldn't project that on any
system at scale that people should teach
this or should teach that i i would
actually let them figure that out
um that's that sort of part of my
philosophy of life is is
i'll only push things at a scale that
that
uh couldn't succeed if they were not at
that scale right
so you know it's tempting to say yeah
everyone should learn it but but
um it's it's too important to me to have
independence among
those kinds of decisions um so
so no i would not project that in any
global sense that people should learn
that
um but i i would do it personally
um and core concepts so
the core concepts that really come up
over and over are you know i think
having an understanding of what is meant
by reductionism what do we really mean
when we say that that
um someone is applying reductionism to
some system
then once you kind of grasp that you can
see the complement more easily you can
see okay if that's what this is then
then what is the other thing
one of the examples i really like um for
for
talking about reductionism and the
failure of reductionism
is if you know this um geometric idea of
a mobius strip
which is like kind of take a strip of
paper and almost like you're going to
put the strip of paper in a loop
but you spin it 180 degrees you kind of
twist it
you know halfway and connect it back to
itself
and the thing that that produces
geometrically sort of
just in mathematical abstract space is
an object that's
one-sided so the piece of paper we feel
is kind of two-sided there's this side
of the paper there's that side of the
paper
but when you have a mobius strip you
actually if you for instance put a
pencil on it and start
drawing on the surface there would be no
other side to draw a line on you'd get
kind of the both sides of that paper
without ever lifting your pencil off
right um
now interestingly let's say i was
interested in that property so maybe
i'm going to now be a reductionist and
i'm going to try to figure out where
that property comes from by cutting that
movie strip up into parts well the
moment i cut that mobius strip into any
parts that are smaller than the whole
thing
i now have parts that are two-sided not
one-sided
so every part of the system every local
piece of the system is two-sided
but the global piece of the system is
one-sided so you so you see very quickly
how
trying to understand this by pulling it
into parts and and studying them
is never going to get you there um so so
this idea of reductionism
and the failure of reductionism and what
you get then are things called emergent
properties
um those are some of the core concepts
and then
probably the other sort of major major
concept is this idea of
self-organization
so what's making the mobius strip
one-sided is the organization
of the whole system or object
and um but where does that organization
come from
well for a mobius strip it comes from
the mind of mobius
but for many things in the world where
we're looking at properties that arising
from the organization of the system
there is no external agent who's
constructing the system taking the
pieces and putting them into the right
places
the pieces are actually interacting and
putting themselves into the
right places or putting themselves into
wherever they end up
and so this idea of self-organization of
organization that that that arises
spontaneously
that's not uh dictated by by a planner
or a constructor
or however you want to call it um that's
sort of the other
major major theme that that i would hit
on if i were trying to teach people
about just the core
uh concepts of complexity
joe i'm kind of getting the feeling that
even this description of complexity is
kind of like trying to take a concept
that you have to understand the whole of
it
and bringing it into little chunks like
with each of these questions you're like
well here's one aspect of it and here's
another aspect and if we were able to
understand each of these different
pieces we might be able to sort of grok
that whole thing there
i mean i'm just that's absolutely
correct i mean so so complexity the
topic complexities
itself has many facets it's like this
hyper-dimensional object and there's
like an infinite number of perspectives
you could
kind of travel and look at it and every
perspective will kind of highlight
different things and hide other things
and and that's exactly right and i don't
think there is a
ultimate hole to be grasped frankly i
don't think that i've grocked the whole
i don't think anyone has
i think that everyone who's involved is
kind of looking from
a perspective or a set of perspectives
and we're all kind of putting little
pieces of that together
and over time you kind of get these uh
sort of phase transition aha moments
where you've seen enough different
angles or you go oh i
get how those are connected now i'm
understanding the relations among these
different concepts
but there's always like it's like kind
of like spiraling outwards you kind of
travel around and see the perspective
again and you're always kind of
backing up a little further and kind of
seeing a little more and getting the
bigger picture but i don't think there's
an end to that process
i mean for me uh studying complexity has
been the ultimate
uh humility inducer it's like the moment
you think that you kind of
understand things like no you don't
there's there's
more subtleties there's there's more
there's more to go
awesome and i think this totally fits in
with um
with kevin's question as well so kevin
deland do you want to read out your
question
sure awesome hey joe great i love this
so far
um so complexity is biased nature
non-one year has many moving parts etc
but many of our current methods of
communicating thinking
and understanding are limited by their
linearity
how do you see the role of new
computer-based mediums
and communicating ideas of complexity to
the general public
some examples might be simulations video
games
interactives explorable explanations etc
and some of these can be especially
useful for communicating
the concepts you mentioned like
immersion properties and
self-organization um so that and do you
see any examples
or have you experienced any examples
that you find particularly promising
interesting so for one i'm not sure that
i
buy into the assumption that all our
ways of communicating are linear
i mean i think that we're involved in
highly non-linear
interactions all the time every time we
speak to one another um
so that's one thing i'd say um with
respect to technology
and kind of communicating these ideas
well i'll put a plug-in for myself
here i'm actually um starting up an
online course
i'm going to run the first session this
fall actually starting next week
um i'm going to run it synchronous kind
of like this stoa meeting because i
really think
you know as we're doing right now uh
the the mooc kind of pre-packaged video
courses they they're they're good
i use them for things and not trying to
uh hate on them or anything but
they lack something really essential and
that is that as we're able to kind of
interact and communicate
um we are able to surface things
and and and kind of get to the point in
a way that you can't with a sort of a
one-directional communication like um
like like um a post-it video or
something
so um i'm gonna run that course and my
plan is to run more of those sessions
and more courses some more in-depth
technical courses as well in the future
so if anyone is interested in that uh
please do check that out
um and other than that i mean i think
that
for all of its ills and everything that
maybe negative you can point to
the the advent of social media really
this development uh
moving beyond broadcast media into this
two-way communication and and everyone
is kind of a broadcaster and a receiver
um i think is really uh something
really important for us to to evolve to
as a species
and right now i think that we're
experiencing a lot of the instabilities
that it's
inducing um but those
instabilities are a consequence of
moving
out of the previous stabilities of
broadcast media
and broadcast media is is inherently
unnatural i mean when you imagine where
do we come from we don't come from
a uh history where there there's
large-scale broadcast media there's no
way to kind of
um centralize a message and and kind of
force coherence on a mass population
that was a very brief moment in history
in fact that that was a thing and now
it's over again and it's ending we're
transitioning out of it um
so i think social media is is a huge um
gain in in starting to communicate some
of these ideas and other ideas and
figuring out who we are and what we're
about what we're trying to do
um hopefully we can kind of pass through
some of the strife that that we're
experiencing as we
destabilize and and re-stabilize on
something
hopefully not horrific frankly but we'll
see um
and as far as as games and simulations
i'm certain that that um
they could be helpful for some folks to
to kind of
gain intuition around some of the
concepts ideas and maybe it's something
worth pursuing but
it's not uh where i've naturally
gone towards but i can imagine i could
imagine it it could be really cool to
have some games that really highlight
some of these ideas
we're gonna go to dan feldman next
getting lots of plus ones
hi um my
question is as the world is inherently
interconnected and interrelated and at
least to me obviously
complex i i also studied complexity uh
when i was studying electrical
engineering um
how has the education system and the
dominant meta-narrative
kept most of humanity unable to see the
complexity
and then i add in a little addendum here
i think that an argument i live for 10
years in china so
i have that's a little bit of background
here i think that an argument could be
made that taoism and buddhism
and their non-dualistic uh mindsets
together with
the chinese pictographs have enabled
them to avoid reductionism
far more easily
so i i don't feel i can speak to
what exactly the education system has
done that's prevented people from
from kind of seeing things in a certain
way but i do think there's something to
what you're saying
with respect to sort of eastern
philosophies and ways of understanding
are much more naturally inclined to to
see kind of the holism
and the way in which reductionism
doesn't doesn't uh
yield all the answers um
once again this is sort of the second
question around education system and i
feel i feel fundamentally
incapable of making recommendations or
comments on large-scale educational
approaches
i think i mean for one thing people are
unique i think we fail in that
we don't apply enough apprenticeship
type models to pretty much anything um
we we're sort of we think in terms of
kind of
information download as if there's sort
of this information inside of the
teacher's head and they just need to
transfer to the students
when really i mean even even the most
abstract
of endeavors like mathematics is
inherently an embodied activity
and one of the ways that you learn about
it get better at it have insights around
it is to spend time around people doing
math
and and not for them necessarily to tell
you here's what to do here's how to do
it
here's how i think it's just to spend
time around them and
and kind of soak it in and i think
that's what apprenticeship
is in part i mean apprenticeship enables
the
adaptation of a mentor to a protege say
but it also is really about just that
very high bandwidth
um communication that that um
a lot of subtle sort of embodied details
that are very difficult to articulate
and even very
difficult to parse in perception yet
there there's a transference that
happens um
so yeah i can't i can't speak much
uh to the the pictographs um and sort of
chinese um
influences that allow them to see that
but i definitely have more more than i
have an understanding of why that's the
case i haven't noticed that that is the
case
and i've also noticed it with uh folks
from india
that there's a lot of uh indians who
sort of
inherently say oh yeah of course like i
get that like that's that makes sense to
me whereas
um people from western culture is not as
much or it's often
there's more unlearning that needs to
happen there's a lot of
seems to be a lot of mental models that
are actually getting in the way that
that need to be unlearned
okay let's go to joe rivera
you guys can hear me yep yep okay cool
uh thanks for coming out it's been
really cool um my
question comes because um i was sort of
first exposed to this stuff
from nasim taleb stuff and through him i
found you in a bunch of your work
um and it seems to me as someone you
know knew to all of this relatively
that televis had a lot of success in the
last decade and sort of bringing this
way of thinking to a lot more people and
almost you could say to the mainstream
and i was just wondering for the people
who are
unfamiliar with the whole literature
around complexity chaos theory
cybernetics like
just starting places like besides you
know the whole ensured
intruder series um for non-technical
people
to like actually sink their teeth in
because like you said
reading those books it feel it gets to
feel like
embodied and you start to like see the
things out in the world
and i was just wondering if you had any
other thinkers writers whatever
that someone could actually sink their
teeth in and embody this further
i'll just throw you a handful of my
favorite fingers that
pop off the top of my head um i love stu
kaufman
um i i his idea of
the adjacent possible and think about
evolution as
this sort of non-ergotic uh stepping
into new possibility space all the time
um
along with many of his other thoughts
you know auto catalytic sets
as sort of the foundation of life so stu
kaufman
um is a great person to to look into
chris alexander who is an architect
and who sees that the way
in modern times that we construct
buildings
that we design and construct buildings
is
fundamentally different than the way
it's been done historically
and it produces things that often feel
alienating or might be perceived as ugly
and
certainly don't kind of fit into the
context that they're in in the way that
pretty much every building through
history did for for a time
um so i love chris alexander timeless
way of building um
is is a book that really um
impacted me and i've read it a number of
times and every time i read it it's
i get something else out of it it's one
of those kinds of books
um i'm a big fan of robert rosen who's
um even lesser known than these other
guys um
his book in particular life itself i
really um the
the treatment not only of the thesis
that he develops
but the way he um articulates and treats
uh reductionism and and and the
scientific enterprise and what we're
doing when we
model natural systems with formal
language
and how those interrelate i think is
really
it's one of those things where you read
it and you say oh yeah of course i think
i always knew that but i'm not sure
um so those are three names
yeah three is good right
but uh you know feel free to reach out
anytime if you
want to talk more about it okay yeah
sure will do thank you i appreciate that
sure and if other people on the call
have ideas or recommendations feel free
to throw them in the chat as well
yeah and like i said you know i
mentioned steven strogatz already that's
a
that was um the book sync is stephen
straught is a mathematician but it's a
non-technical read
and it's a little more it reads a little
more like a pop-sci book but i think the
the ideas are solid and he's a solid guy
and you said you were reading that in
your bathroom i think yep yep i
have a very vivid memory of picking up
out of a basket
sitting on the throne i'm just wondering
like you said your dad was from
complexity as well like i'm just
picturing what kind of house you must
have grown up in
i won't say much more i think he's
actually on the call oh
that's wonderful um i've got a question
here from uh from brett
he says i'm feeling a remark that covid
is just the beginning of some kind of
collapse
season with fires burning etc what are
most what are the most crisis-prone
systems right now
that you feel are blocked by
reductionism and need
immediate rethinking since it's not
clear that most of us can do the
homesteading
thing what might we be able to do to
help mitigate
um this these uh there's there's more of
the question but that's sort of like
where i'll leave it
yeah so i mean i mean just the
low-hanging fruit on this
is it didn't seem like we learned how to
deal with a pandemic at all
so that's still one of our biggest
threats
i mean it's kind of it's kind of
incredible you know we're arguing over
is it as bad as we thought is it worse
than we thought are there long-term
effects
we should be saying hey if this was even
worse
we're this isn't good if this was even
worse you know
how screwed would we be and what could
we do differently to be to be
you know do a little better and survive
um
so pandemic is is still going um
the interdependency the economic
interdependency of goods and services
i mean the amount of negative
externalities that we
produce by by doing the all these global
trades where that don't have to be
global i mean i'm not
opposed to you know someone makes
something
in india and i want to purchase it and
there's a system put sent into the mail
that's that's great and i don't have an
issue with that
but doing everything at scale where all
of my food is coming from
very far away and all of my material
goods are coming from very far away i
mean
it only takes a few little disruptions
in that until where the hell am i going
to get what i need to
actually live um what can people do not
everyone can adopt a homesteading
lifestyle
well for one thing i think more people
could adopt a homesteading lifestyle
or at least um there's there's it's not
the case that there couldn't be some
kind of a
uh rural revival where young people do
move out to the country and
and make things happen and i would love
to see that and i encourage it
um but in all environments i mean urban
environments are not going anywhere
either this is a natural part
of of being human is having urban
environments
you you know i've lived i've lived in
urban environments i've lived in
cambridge mass you can find
farms that are just outside the city you
can change the way you grocery shop
you can uh decide not to to order that
thing from around the world and look on
even any even things that are like etsy
where you're like oh it's like a
small artisanal maker of product x or i
can order it from amazon
order from the small artisanal maker so
it's really those like little decisions
and i think even going on a larger scale
um
knowing that the people here or i'm
making an assumption that some of the
people here are thinking
in terms of like where to actually
intervene in the system um
i'm hoping to pass things over to morgan
carter to ask his question
cool um so how do you decide how best to
intervene
in a complex system particularly ones
that are too complex
to to wrap your head around and how do
you make good decisions
and how do you judge the outcome of
those decisions without
resorting to reductionist metrics and i
can give an example here
if that helps i was working recently on
a project um
working within an organization about 600
people and it became clear after a
couple of weeks that
no one in the organization knew what the
organization was doing there was too
many
things going on so it became quite hard
to
make good decisions within the context
of that project and then to judge them
after the fact
and i'm wondering if the complexity
science says anything that can help
tackle that sure so um
i mean if you can't judge if you've gone
to a better
place than where you were before then
you are kind of in trouble
because you need to at least have a
selection criteria have things gotten
better have things gotten worse
so i don't know of any shortcut around
that specifically
um the non-shortcut around that is
i mean depending it depends what your
organization does but there's some uh
something there's either an end user or
something analogous to like an end user
so i mean you really want to
have as little proxy to that step as
possible in terms of judging is this
better is this worse
well what does the user say um
that's kind of the ground truth in a
sense um
but in general um because you can't wrap
your head around
everything going on you need to create a
you need to make a facsimile of
evolution where you're creating a
selective environment of some kind and
exactly the selection
is that end user or some as close to
that as you can get
where it's judging better worse better
worse and you're not worried so much
about exactly how
those pieces fit together to produce
that better thing
you only care that it's better um in
more generally uh with respect to
intervention
you you need to consider well what kind
of a system am i working with what is
the intervention i'm proposing
and if something went wrong with this
intervention what would be the scope of
harm
that would that i can expect um and the
other way think about it sort of what
puts the upper bound on that scope of
harm
what what stops the harm from spreading
if it can spread
um and then you need to be okay with
uh intervening where failure is
tolerable
and where the scope of failure is
tolerable and
there's really there's really no
shortcut to that
it's kind of the long trudge of
evolution
so so i mean intervening
is always some kind of an uncertainty
injection
yeah that's basically what i found i was
hoping there was some shortcut
but i guess not it's it's it's
rather than hoping there's a shortcut
it's
making decisions understanding there's
not and uh
thinking in terms of of how do i
like i said how do i select and how do i
fail and which kind of failures
can i tolerate and which kind of
failures can i not
i think for me i'm almost thinking of it
in terms of like
run like looking at it as different
experiments that one might run
like if i poke the system in this way
what happens am i allowed to poke it
this way am i worried if i poke it this
way
what sort of comes up and what does this
tell me about the thing that i'm looking
at
in terms of its emergent behaviors right
i mean yeah with the complex system
there's
no no way to learn about it without
perturbing it without without poking it
and and seeing what happens um so
that that's why i say you know you need
to think about the failure mode and like
if i poked it here and you know
something starts spreading from there
is that bad does that hurt things can i
tolerate it if it
keeps spreading is there anything to
stop it spreading if it if it does
and and you know the other thing that
i'll say and this is you know this is
really from the scene
uh talib is um
if you're you can choose to not
intervene that's a choice you can make
as well
and often that's actually a good choice
let things
uh living systems heal
and you have to let them heal and if you
keep poking a wound
it doesn't heal um now
if you're bleeding out okay you
intervene
close up the wound right so when things
get really extreme
sort of existentially extreme where you
might
the system might perish then intervene
away
go for it you know put all your chips in
but other than that you might actually
step back and let things
uh resolve of their own accord and i
think we don't do nearly enough of that
in the modern world
it's obviously not a solution to
everything obviously
but we air very much on the other side
of things
we are constantly trying to intervene to
make the thing right
and that is actually a guarantee that
the system will never
sort of settle down into some kind of a
stable dynamic equilibrium
it will continue to destabilize the
system and you'll be
chasing uh the sort of
you know as you destabilize you're
getting these excursions away from some
stable point
you're going to keep chasing the system
around if you're intervening too much
too often
and not letting the forces resolve
themselves
so i think we have time for one more
question
um yeah
i think i'd like to go to ann jen you
asked a question
significantly earlier i'm wondering if
you'd like to to read that question out
i think that would be a good one to end
on
hey joe um hey i i feel like
i've read a couple of these books i go
to these lectures and i get pretty
excited
um and i just am terrible at applying it
into
my life like i still make the same
stupid decisions the way i understand
news the way i
pick things to buy the way i plan my day
my week blah blah blah
i'm curious how it went from something
that you were intellectually fascinated
by
to actually like embodying and
integrating it into your life and kind
of
mental habits if there was like events
or things
that were inflection points that would
be cool if you shared
oh i i don't think that there has been
any kind of inflection point that i can
identify
everything has been a small step it's
been a series of small small steps
right now you know i'm saying we're out
here homesteading
you know what homesteading looked like
yesterday is different than what it
looks like tomorrow
and usually that's in the right
direction sometimes it's not
uh we had to fire on our property
earlier this year
and that set us back quite a bit because
we're still rebuilding from that and
getting back to where we were in a lot
of ways
other things can progress alongside it
in parallel and that's that's good and
we have but
with respect to having some of the
outbuildings that were serving some
functions for us
that's uh we're set back quite a ways um
and i guess you know taking the leap of
moving to essentially the middle of
nowhere
i guess could be almost like an
inflection point but it doesn't feel
that way because
up until like we started we said hey we
want to
learn how to produce our own food we
neither myself nor my wife
had ever done that in our lives uh we
didn't know what
the hell we were doing um so we started
a little container garden
in in the back of the little house we
were renting
and you know i i remember so so here's
maybe an inflection point
emotionally at least i don't know if it
really is but um
we plant we put some soil and like egg
cartons and we planted some little
tomato seeds
and that was the first thing we planted
and we had them like sit in the kitchen
on top of the refrigerator
and i remember when those first sprouts
went and we were like
holy you know the most almost in a
sense it's like the most mundane thing
on earth like this happens all the time
everywhere this is nothing uh remarkable
at all
but in other sense obviously the the um
genesis of a living pattern out of this
little seed is
quite remarkable and for me emotionally
i think for my wife as well
it was just kind of a hey
this is almost like nothing but it's
amazingly gratifying to even see this
and it's kind of doing itself i mean we
gave it the conditions but it's kind of
going itself
and so okay yeah we brought those
seedlings up and
planted some other ones and started a
container garden and started eating from
it
all of a sudden we're eating from from
our little container garden and then
that's
starting to reinforce wow we can really
do this um
so i think that combined with at that
same time we also
enrolled in our first csa which if you
don't know what that is it's uh
stands for community supported
agriculture and it means that basically
you buy
like a subscription to a farm and every
week or whatever their timing is
you get like a box of stuff from them i
mean different farms running different
details but
the essential idea is you get some share
of vegetables
and you know if they have a really bad
season then your share might suck and
that's why it's community supported
agriculture right because you're not
getting a guarantee in any sense of what
you're really going to get out of it
but my experience is most the time you
get amazing vegetables so at that same
time we also did that
and we started visiting the farms that
we're getting uh the csa from
and um that was also
really like a moment where we were like
all right this is like we're changing
what we're doing we stopped eating
random junk from the store um
so there was there's some moments that
were like really kind of
felt like aha moments but i but when i
look at the actual history and
progression of things i mean everything
has been a very small step
thanks joe so i'm going to leave that as
our last question for today
um and i think what would give me a
sense of completeness here is just to
invite everyone on the call to sort of
look at what you're feeling right now at
the
end of today's session as we attempted
to grok with
applied complexity and put one or two
words about sort of like
what's what you're feeling right now and
just feel free to drop that into the
chat and i think
that's gonna be like a nice way for me
to see am i
are you guys all feeling the same thing
that i am which is like
a sense of curiosity and like i'm
feeling driven to
keep exploring more into this complexity
topic
and i'll also invite peter lindberg to
make a couple announcements as well
while we do very cool
uh thank you ryan and thank you so much
joe for visiting the stoa
uh that was great fun thanks for having
me that was awesome
really appreciate it yeah we would love
to have you back
and um so upcoming events uh tomorrow
so as i mentioned we have a sense maker
in residence series so this is someone
comes in for
a month they have four sessions uh we
have dave snowden zack stein vanita
royal coming in
we also have peter wang my boy peter
wang he's doing a series on the mental
models that helped him
navigate the complexity of life and
that's 10 a.m eastern time
tomorrow you can rsvp there we also just
posted an event
depolarizing conversations with richard
bartlett and ronan harrington um that's
september 15th the tuesday at 10 a.m
eastern time
uh and rachel haywire you got an event
tomorrow the philosopher queens
you want to briefly plug it yes sir
raven connolly
and i are having alyssa
come by to the philosopher quinn panel
here at the store
tomorrow night we're going to be
discussing
the divine feminine archetypes the
transcendence of the female form
and what it means to be interacting
with these tonic energies
everybody from kevin palia to
modern philosophers like raven and
alyssa who were going to be here
tomorrow night so
everyone interested in the dark and
divine feminine come on bye
very cool thank you rachel uh you can
check out
okay so much freaking events on the
website you can go onto the website the
store.ca if you'd like to support us on
patreon you can go to our patreon um
link which i'll put in the chat in a
moment that being said joe
everyone thank you so much for coming
stola
thank you peter thank you to ryan thank
you everybody